<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Django on Blog | Federico Marani</title>
    <link>/tags/django/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Django on Blog | Federico Marani</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 12:09:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/django/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial search on multiple points in Solr</title>
      <link>/blog/spatial-search-on-multiple-points-in-solr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 12:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/spatial-search-on-multiple-points-in-solr/</guid>
      <description>At TrialReach we deal with clinical trials data, which contain a lot of spatial information. Tipically, clinical trials treat a certain set of conditions and they happen in various locations globally. If you are a patient then searching across clinical trials becomes really spatial sensitive: you are only interested in the closest location to you.
This case might apply to other events as well, but the key point is global distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology behind tools.seogadget.co.uk</title>
      <link>/blog/technology-behind-toolsseogadgetcouk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 17:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/technology-behind-toolsseogadgetcouk/</guid>
      <description>Scalability was one of the primary concerns when we started building the tool. Essentially, the tool gathers numbers about links you post, it is quite straightforward. To gather these numbers, our tool uses many external APIs and in a way acts as a sort of proxy between the user and many other 3rd party API providers, on top of which some internal indicators are derived. Many tools allow you to do that, but, regarding scalability, some ways are better than others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic things to do and not in Django</title>
      <link>/blog/basic-things-to-do-and-not-in-django/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 19:33:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/basic-things-to-do-and-not-in-django/</guid>
      <description>Make software dependent on absolute paths: One of the projects i was working on had all module imports including the project main folder name. That in turn made impossible to have the same project installed 2 times in the same folder with 2 distinct names. (e.g. 2 versions of the staging site). Sometime is even worse than this, when you have a full path in the code. These should always be in configuration files which are changeable at deployment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>