<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>startups on Blog | Federico Marani</title>
    <link>/tags/startups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in startups on Blog | Federico Marani</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2017 16:30:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimalism is how startups keep the focus</title>
      <link>/blog/minimalism-is-how-startups-keep-focus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2017 16:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/minimalism-is-how-startups-keep-focus/</guid>
      <description>I want to blog about this topic because minimalism, meant as the art of doing only the essential, is a very hard thing to do. Writing about things helps me with having a clear mind. I will therefore try to write about it, and rewrite about it in the future as many times as my thinking clears up.
I realize this article will leave you with a ton of space for interpretation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YCombinator interview</title>
      <link>/blog/yc-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 20:43:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/yc-interview/</guid>
      <description>A month ago me and my co-founder did an application for YC, and last week we were lucky enough to be selected for an interview, along with other startups. We got called all the way to California with not even a week of notice, everything paid&amp;hellip; definitely a bit more serious than a phone call.
We prepared a lot during the last few days, reading what people say online, meeting previous YC companies, doing mock interviews with YC alumni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another failure, another lesson - comprotempo.it</title>
      <link>/blog/comprotempo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/comprotempo/</guid>
      <description>When it came out, I was fashinated by TaskRabbit. I thought that a generic marketplace for handymen was the perfect tool for this decade. We have lots of young unemployment in Italy and there were also middle-class people willing to pay for someone doing chores for them. The idea was simple: putting both sides in touch by agreeing location, type of task and price. The advantages for handymen were money for work, the advantages for the committant is to &amp;ldquo;buy&amp;rdquo; someone else&amp;rsquo;s time (hence the &amp;ldquo;comprotempo&amp;rdquo; name)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>