<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>startup on Blog | Federico Marani</title>
    <link>/tags/startup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in startup on Blog | Federico Marani</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 15:24:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/startup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why my first startup failed - tabs.to</title>
      <link>/blog/why-my-first-startup-failed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 15:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/why-my-first-startup-failed/</guid>
      <description>Tabs.to was a url shortener, but with a twist, it could support multiple urls and it was displaying them with a sort of tabbed interface which you could use to switch between pages. The use case I was seeing was sending multiple links via twitter, and by doing so you would have saved space. In hindsight, it seems pretty short-sighted but that was the problem I had. This was in 2010, 4 years ago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From idea to a product</title>
      <link>/blog/from-idea-to-a-product/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 00:28:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/from-idea-to-a-product/</guid>
      <description>This is my history in one of the first startups I worked for, very small, but nevertheless a very good learning experience.
Selling the idea We had the vision, and we sold our vision in the way a lean startup would do: sell the vision, receive funding for the project, deliver the product. Turns out it is extremely hard to sell something that does not exist, but we did it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why SOA in a startup sucks</title>
      <link>/blog/why-soa-in-a-startup-sucks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2012 21:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/why-soa-in-a-startup-sucks/</guid>
      <description>Service Oriented Architectures as i intend are architectures where each component is deployable and usable separately from others. Take as example Amazon, much of their software stack is offered as a service, mainly through an HTTP interface, and marketed as SaaS.
There are tons of reasons why you would want to think to your system as a series of components deployable separately&amp;hellip; flexibility, being able to choose the right tools for each component, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>